<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: NaNoWriMo | Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/categories/nanowrimo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-01T08:04:16-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excerpt from Pacifica]]></title>
    <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/12/01/excerpt-from-pacifica/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T07:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/12/01/excerpt-from-pacifica</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the best study of my main character, the one that I think most accurately captures who she thinks she is. </p>

<hr />

<p>The roadway sparkles and flows with light, a jeweled strand across the dark landscape. Cylee sat far up on a hill, the fresh, wild wind blowing her hair back. </p>

<p>She used to live in this place, this quiet, dark, outdoor world. Back before Pacifica, before the war…</p>

<p>The strings of lights eventually merge into the cities, connecting the nets of lights that represent civilization, mankind’s crowning jewels shining in the dark. And once you’re caught in that net it can feel like there’s nothing else, no other way to live. You can learn to depend on the Network, constant wireless streams of information flowing into and out of you at all times. You can learn to read the streets as you read the trees, feel the way the social wind is blowing just as you used to know how to read the fitful pre-dawn breezes. </p>

<p>And, in truth, Cylee was caught by that net. If she stayed out here for a few days or weeks her Spine would shut down and go from being an Augmentation to being thirty pounds of stiff dead metal. She’d be essentially blinded and deafened, her limbs left to their own strength. Even now she was half blind, her Spine out of range of the Network and therefore unable to give her the kind of information that made up the background noise of her daily life. Granted, she could still see every living, warm blooded thing that moved in the darkness, every rabbit, every bat, every bird was a blip on her augmented vision, their insane heart rates pounding like miniature thunder in her ears. </p>

<p>But she used to track them unaided. Used to be able to sense the movement of creatures that were string to remain hidden. She could feel the twitch in the grass that didn’t <em>quite</em> match the way the wind was moving. And she would raise her bow quietly, wait for the next movement…and…with a soft twang she would have breakfast.</p>

<p>Out of a sense of irony and frustration she considered raising her flechette thrower and pinning that rabbit to the ground, letting her Spine handle the fine details of getting her hand in the right position, but she stopped, realized she didn’t need the meat, and shouldn’t waste it. Pacifica had made her a perfect soldier, but it hadn’t entirely removed the true hunter she had been. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My NaNoWriMo Cover for This Year]]></title>
    <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/10/31/my-nanowrimo-cover-for-this-year/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-31T11:34:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/10/31/my-nanowrimo-cover-for-this-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/assets/images/pacifica_cover.jpg" width="250" title="Pacifica Cover" >
This is a super-short post to show off what I’m going to be working on for <a href="http://nanowrimo.org">NaNoWriMo</a> this year. </p>

<p>I know that <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim/">Painless Vim</a></em> isn’t finished yet, although it’s very close, and basically all I’m doing is a little bit of cleanup and formatting. If you’ve been waiting with baited breath for <em>Painless Vim</em> to be finished fear not! I will still be working on the Little Vim Book that Could during the month of November. In fact, my goal is to have it completely finished. By December 1st, even while I’m “winning” NaNoWriMo for the sixth straight year. </p>

<p>In previous years I’ve been doing graduate level classes, having babies<sup id="fnref:babies"><a href="#fn:babies" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and changing jobs during NaNoWriMo, and I’ve always found time to make it work. What’s more, the impetus it gives me tends to help me get more done in the rest of my life as well. The saying about giving work to busy people still holds true. If I turn myself into a busy person I tend to be more capable overall. Until I freak out and melt down, of course. So I guess there’s still something to be said for balance. </p>

<h2 id="more-about-pacifica">More About Pacifica</h2>

<p>Which is all very nice, but you may possibly be interested in the book cover I’m showing off here. You’ve got questions, no doubt. Questions like “What’s it about?” “Who designed your cover?” “Would you be willing to let me redesign your cover, because it’s pretty bad?” </p>

<p>The answers are “I’ll tell you in a minute”, “I did in about two hours using Pixelmator”, and “Yes” in that order. I like playing with Pixelmator, but I’m not super great with it, and if there’s a graphic designer out there who wants to take a second pass at this I’d be happy to let you. </p>

<p>The book is my first foray into cyberpunk. It’s a near-future look at what’s its like to be on the losing side of a war for independence, and how to keep your pride even when you’ve got nothing left to be proud of. </p>

<p>If I remember (and have time) I’ll probably post excerpts through the month. Wether or not I actually develop <em>Pacifica</em> after November remains to be seen, but if I’ve learned anything from five successful NaNo’s its that even writing an ultimately wasted story isn’t wasted effort. I’ve learned something from every book I’ve written.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:babies">
      <p>Well, not me <em>personally</em>. <a href="#fnref:babies" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
