<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-07T13:31:01-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://natedickson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Walking Home With Chicago Avenue Moon]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/05/07/walking-home-with-chicago-avenue-moon/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-07T11:06:37-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/05/07/walking-home-with-chicago-avenue-moon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/Chicago-Avenue-Moon_web.png" title="Chicago Avenue Moon Icon" />
Heading out, leaving work. It’s about two miles home, an easy half-hour walk. What’s more, it’s all downhill. I decide to let Chicago Avenue Moon do its thing while I walk. Let’s hear some procedurally generated tunes. </p>

<p>The UI doesn’t tell me much; or rather, it <em>does</em>, but not in a way that I can understand. A string of numbers running down one side of the screen slowly starts filling in, going from all <code>0.00</code> to…other numbers. Probably based on my walking speed? A line swings across four circles, highlighting them…and that’s it. But it’s time to put the device away, time to walk. </p>

<p>The sound starts slowly…a quiet susurrous of static is all for a moment, then a gentle swell of strings, maybe?</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/CAM-Screen.png" title="Screenshot from Chicago Avenue Moon" />
Slowly the sonic landscape fills in: quiet, layered sounds give way to rising waves of music. It’s like having an audio-only link to some other world. This isn’t music I’ve heard a thousand times before, this is something new and unique, being created by my walk, and it opens my eyes. </p>

<p>I’ve seen everything along this route hundreds of times, but I’m seeing it more clearly this time. Bright, living green grasses under a mottled gray cloudy sky. I’m more aware of colors than I’ve been in a long time, I’m open to the feeling of the wind…and presently the rain.</p>

<p>I pull my umbrella out of my messenger bag and pop it open, imagining what I might look like from above. A drab, office-worker colored stalk, watered by the rain, suddenly bursts into a bright red and white flower fighting the wind. </p>

<p>The sounds of wind and rain fold themselves into the music from Chicago Avenue, and in my quiet and dreamlike state it’s easy to believe that whatever mathematical equations are controlling the sounds are also orchestrating the storm, for as soon as I turn a corner the rain slows, then stops. The music, too, changes gradually, adapting to my new position and heading. The whoosh and hiss of cars driving past in the rain…it’s all one.</p>

<p>At length I turn the corner onto my street, and one by one the layers of music fall away, leaving only a slow, stately tone, rolling in grand waves, and fading slightly, a fitting end to a walk in another world. </p>

<hr />

<p><a href="http://junecloud.com/software/iphone/chicago-avenue-moon.html"> <em>Chicago Avenue Moon</em> </a> is an oddity on the App Store. Created by <a href="http://junecloud.com">JuneCloud</a>, who are best known for their <a href="http://junecloud.com/software/iphone/delivery-status-touch.html"> package tracking app </a>, it’s a pure work of art, and one that succeeds. According to the website, it was originally the vision of <a href="http://quieterrors.com/">Joshua Dumas</a>, a musician who wanted to </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…help re-enchant a person’s daily commute, trip to the laundromat, or evening jog. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>A worthy goal. </p>

<p>The app really does create a soundscape that is throbbing with life, full of strange, alien combinations, and occasionally overlaid with bursts of static, as if you really were channeling this music from somewhere far away.</p>

<p>It may not be the perfect soundtrack for every single day, but if you want to include a little bit of mystery into your daily wanderings it’s definitely worth a try.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing With the Alphasmart NEO]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/03/07/writing-with-the-alphasmart-neo/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T09:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/03/07/writing-with-the-alphasmart-neo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/NEO.jpg" width="400" height="400" title="The Alphasmart Neo in its natural habitat" />
A thing I once thought would never happen has happened twice: I have been paid for something I wrote by people who actually ponied up their own hard-earned cash to buy <a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">a thing I wrote</a>. I can’t even tell you how awesome that is. If you are one of those people I thank you from the bottom of my heart. </p>

<p>But that’s not what this article is about. This article is about what I did with the second royalty check I got from Leanpub a few days ago:</p>

<p>I bought an Alphasmart NEO. </p>

<p>I first became aware of the existence of these little wonders when I was reading Chris Baty’s<sup id="fnref:whoIsChris"><a href="#fn:whoIsChris" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> book “No Plot? No Problem!”. Says he:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some NaNoWriMo participants swear by an affordable machine called an Alphasmart (www.alphasmart.com). This is a battery-powered, word-processing device that looks like a cross between a laptop and a children’s Speak &amp; Spell. The miniscule screen only displays four lines of text or so at a time, which can be helpful in warding off obsessive editing. The keyboard is large and comfortable, and you can work for up to twenty-six hours on a few AA batteries.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>– Baty, Chris (2010-07-01). No Plot? No Problem!: A Low-Stress, High-Velocity Guide to Writing a Novel in 30 Days (p. 74). Chronicle Books LLC. Kindle Edition. </p>

<p>“Yes. This is a right thing. This is genius,” I muttered quietly to myself. Here was something that embodied the ideal of “one thing well”. A concept that I’ve always loved, all the more because I’m so terribly bad at sticking to one thing for any length of time. </p>

<p>When I first read this the NEO2 was still a current concern, priced around $200, which was out of my price range, or rather outside of the budget I could concieveably justify on a writing toy. So I shelved the idea of owning one for a while and went on with my life.</p>

<p>And wrote <a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a>. And got paid for it, twice now. Not a lot, mind you<sup id="fnref:yet"><a href="#fn:yet" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, but actual cash money. Which means I have a little money to spend on writing toys. But when I went back to the Alphasmart website I discovered that the Neo’s time had come to a close.</p>

<p>The NEO is no longer being manufactured. The company has shut down that arm of their business, and all that’s left is second-hand models that schools are getting rid of, as near as I can tell. But that’s a blessing for someone like me, because the price on a second-hand model on eBay is usually in the $40-$60 range. After a few hours of looking at all the different models that Alphasmart had ever made, comparing them and learning far more about them than I had previously thought possible I found one at the right price and a deal was struck. </p>

<h2 id="about-the-neo">About the NEO</h2>

<p>The NEO is a device that was designed to fulfill a very specific role: it is for <em>writing</em>. It is not for web surfing, it doesn’t have a browser or even a network interface. It’s not for games, it’s got a very simple display that can show you around six lines of text at a time. It’s not for reading email. It is only for <em>writing</em>. </p>

<p>Being designed for the classroom has other advantages. Alphasmart products are legendarily rugged, built to withstand grade school students long enough to justify the school board’s expenditure on them. They are an instant-on device, because there’s no real OS to load up. Turn it on, write. They are the most energy conscious devices ever: Several owners claim they will run for <em>seven hundred hours</em> on a fresh set of 3 AA batteries. So far I’ve used my device for about 20 hours and I’m at around 98% battery, so that sounds surprisingly accurate. </p>

<p>Granted, the NEO is not a machine with great specs. For starters, it has 512K of RAM, which is charming. My Macbook Pro has roughly 33,000 times that much. But that 512K is enough to hold about 200 pages of text, split out over 8 files. When all you’re doing is writing you don’t need a lot of storage space. Text is small. </p>

<p>Equally charming is the NEO-computer interface: plug the NEO in via USB and the computer will recognize it as a keyboard. So you open Word or Scrivener or your favorite text program on your computer, put the cursor where you want the text and press “send” on the NEO. Suddenly the computer thinks the NEO is a keyboard where someone is typing at around 200 words per minute. </p>

<p>And that is the <em>whole point</em> of the device. It’s focused, so it can do it’s “one thing” well. It’s rugged, so it can go camping. It’s inexpensive, so if it turns out that taking it camping was a bad idea you can replace it without too much heartache. And did I mention that it’s a very <em>focused</em> device? When you are writing on a NEO you can’t be sneaking peeks at your email, or twitter or anything else. All you can do is write. It’s the perfect middle step between a paper notebook and a MacBook.</p>

<p>It also imparts a strange and wonderful sense of detachment from the writing grind. Everything you write disappears off the top of the screen in a matter of moments, leaving you with just your most recent thought and maybe the conclusion of the one before it. More than once I have written for an hour or less, and felt like I got a little bit done, plugged the NEO into my computer and watched as thousands of words pour out across the page. Turns out it’s easier to be productive when you’re not worrying about your productivity. </p>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:whoIsChris">
      <p>For those of you who don’t know, Christ Baty is the man who started <a href="http://nanowrimo.org">NaNoWriMo</a>. <a href="#fnref:whoIsChris" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:yet">
      <p>yet. But here’s hoping!<a href="#fnref:yet" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Oyster Books Isn't For Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/03/03/why-oyster-books-isnt-for-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T09:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/03/03/why-oyster-books-isnt-for-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>…yet. </p>

<p>Last Saturday I opened an account. The next day I closed it.</p>

<p>On the surface <a href="https://www.oysterbooks.com/">Oyster Books</a> looks like a great thing: pay $10 every month and get access to a growing library of books. This, you would think, is basically playing right to my wheelhouse. I love books, I love reading, and I love eBooks on my mobile devices. </p>

<p>But it’s not for me. Why is that?</p>

<p>I mean, $9.95 isn’t bad; it’s kinda-sorta the same price as Netflix, and I read far more than I watch in a given month. I could easily read four or five books every month and it would probably be a good thing, right?</p>

<p>Except…</p>

<p>Except what <em>kind</em> of books are on the service? I have a hard enough time finding books I consider “worth reading” on iBooks or Kindle. Anything that is older than the digital age and not über mainstream tends to get forgotten. Anything that has slipped into the public domain is spammed out on the store, thousands of copies, most of them terrible OCR transfers that were never read or reviewed before being shoved onto the store to make a few bucks. </p>

<p>And from what I’ve seen Oyster hasn’t really drawn a different crowd. They have a number of recent best sellers, but a much shallower back bench than the other services, once you remove the <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/wiki/Main_Page">Project Gutenburg</a> rips that everyone has. Oyster has a single Bill Bryson book, the other services have most of his catalog. I could keep going, but the odds are my numbers will all be wrong in a day or two. The <em>point</em> is that I spent a few hours searching Oyster’s catalog for things I really <em>wanted</em> to read and came up with a single book.</p>

<p>But “worth reading” can be a dangerous phrase, and it’s one that doesn’t really sound like <em>me</em> to me. I have spent my life reading just about everything I come across. I’m an author myself, and I should therefore want to stoke the fires of my own literary career by pulling in the best of everyone else’s, right?</p>

<p>Well, yeah. But my time is limited. I work eight hours a day and spend six hours trying to build and maintain a relationship with my wife and kiddos. I squeeze in exercise, games and writing around the edges of this by sleeping between five and seven hours a night. So if I’m going to read a book it needs to be worth the precious minutes I give it. And here’s where a lesson I learned years ago comes back into play.</p>

<p>When I was a teenager I got hired by Bookstar, a small bookstore that was a subsidiary of Barnes and Noble. Shortly after I started at Bookstar we moved into a full-fledged Barnes and Noble superstore. It was a flagship store for the region, and was bigger than any two libraries I had ever visited in my young life. During the early days I would walk through the store in sheer wonder, feeling the immensity of the world’s wisdom, collected around me. I was in heaven. I was surrounded by all that was best and brightest in the world of words.</p>

<p>Except…I wasn’t. The world’s greatest books <em>were</em> in there; we had the entire Loeb Classical Library, both Greek and Latin; the works of Proust and cummings Chesterton and Wodehouse and Feynman and Hawking and Picasso and Miles Davis (in our music department, of course) and the upcoming geniuses as well. But they were thin on the ground compared to the romance novels, serial mysteries, spin-off sci-fi, brainless self-help books<sup id="fnref:disclaimer"><a href="#fn:disclaimer" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>…all the books that look very impressive until you realize that they weren’t written to increase the sum total of human knowledge, they were written to increase the publisher’s bottom line. For every masterpiece that was turned out because the author had a story that <em>must be told</em> there were thirty books that were trying to capitalize on the latest blockbuster. </p>

<p>And I read them. As an employee I was allowed to check books out from the shelves with the understanding that if I bent it I bought it<sup id="fnref:noBend"><a href="#fn:noBend" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. I picked things up joyfully from just about every shelf and read and read and read…and realized that a lot of what I read wasn’t making my life better. I wasn’t any happier, I wasn’t any smarter or any more connected to my fellow human beings. I was just…older. But reading is addictive; even if you’re not in love with the book you’re reading you can still enjoy the experience. So I kept just reading anything, working my way through series after series of 300-page fantasy titles that had all the intelligence of a sitcom, but slower, or through 1,100 page epics that were anything but.</p>

<p>Finally I told myself that my time was worth more, and I needed to read things that were “worth reading”. I got myself a list of “great books” and started into it. Some resonated with me, some didn’t. Some were amazing and some had aged poorly enough that I couldn’t really follow them and lost interest. I still picked up light fantasy titles now and again, but I was determined to change.</p>

<p>So now I generally only read things that I feel have a real point or enough artistry to be worth the time. I say generally, but it’s easy to relapse. I fully recognize that some of my favorite books in recent years are entirely devoid of anything resembling substance or style. And that’s where I get back around to why I probably shouldn’t sign (back) up for Oyster, at least not yet:</p>

<p>I would start reading crap again. </p>

<p>If I was paying ten bucks for a service I would make sure I was getting “my money’s worth” out of the service by ploughing through at least two or three books each month. And I would <em>love</em> it. But I don’t think it would be good for me. </p>

<p>Instead, I’ll just set aside $10 a month for new books. Buying one every a month is about right, and gives me time to catch up on my huge library at home. </p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:disclaimer">
      <p>There are many excellent mystery novels and good sci-fi and good self-help books, I know. But for every good one there are two dozen mindless filler titles that were written by committee. <a href="#fnref:disclaimer" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:noBend">
      <p>Never a problem for me or most of my coworkers. By and large booksellers are a self-selected group made up of people who would gnaw their own arm off rather than dog-ear a page to mark their place. <a href="#fnref:noBend" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trusting VoodooPad]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/01/13/trusting-voodoopad/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T11:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/01/13/trusting-voodoopad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/vp_icon.png" title="VoodooPad Icon" alt="The VoodooPad Icon" />
I’ve <a href="http://www.favoritethingever.com/2010/10/scrivener/">mentioned before</a> that I go through three phases as I get used to a new program: <em>Inquiry</em>, <em>Inquisition</em> and <em>Investment</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <em>Inquiry</em> phase is the “does it do what I want it to do, without being irritating?” phase. Basically this is like a caveman poking a thing with a sharp stick, hiding behind a rock to see if it tries to bite him, then biting <em>it</em> to see if it’s worth eating.</p>

  <p>If a program gets past that, then comes the <em>Inquisition</em>: “Oh yeah, well can you handle <em>this</em>? What about <em>that</em>? And how do you like the <em>comfy chair</em>?”</p>

  <p>Anything that makes it past the Inquisition with any level of approval gets my <em>Investment</em>, the phase where I put the time into learning how to use the program to its fullest and really start using it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve put VoodooPad through the wringer before. Searching through my email reveals that I have a version 2 license<sup id="fnref:password"><a href="#fn:password" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. I liked the idea, the core of VoodooPad back then, but it never got past the Inquisition. I could see that it <em>wanted</em> to do things right, but we never <em>clicked</em>. </p>

<p>Still, when I got the email that VoodooPad had left its original home at Flying Meat I was kinda saddened. It may not have been my cup of tea, but it was still an amazing product and it’s cool in a way that is hard to put into words. Don’t get me wrong, I think Gus of Flying Meat made the right choice when he decided to <a href="http://www.flyingmeat.com/blog/archives/2013/11/a_new_home_for_voodoopad.html">sell VoodooPad</a>. If he doesn’t feel he can maintain it any more nobody would know better than he would. </p>

<p>The new owners at <a href="https://plausible.coop/">Plausible Labs</a> have promised to make it better and take great care of it, because they love VoodooPad and want to see it grow. That’s great news. </p>

<p>But can I trust it?</p>

<p>There’s two questions there: Can I trust Plausible Labs to keep making VoodooPad better, and can I trust VoodooPad to be good enough to deserve my investment?</p>

<p>For the record I’ve already purchased my license; so we’re not talking about <em>financial</em> investment. I’m talking about investing my time, which is far more valuable these days. (“oh, look at Mr. Moneybags!” Yeah, yeah, you know what I meant.)</p>

<p>So, second question first: Can I trust VoodooPad, the program, to be what I want it to be?</p>

<h2 id="trusting-the-program">Trusting the Program</h2>

<p>This is the bigger of the two questions. After all, if VoodooPad is good enough to use and invest in now it doesn’t need a lot of updates all the time. My beloved Scrivener gets (I would say) <em>Just enough</em> updates: Not every month, but every so often. And even if updates stopped tomorrow I would keep using it until it no longer worked on whatever Mac I was using in the far future. </p>

<p>So I’ve started the process. I would say I’m near the end of the Inquisition phase right now. And what I’ve found is hopeful. Coming to version 5 of VoodooPad from version 2 left me refreshingly free of preconceived notions about the program: I knew it was a “Personal Wiki” and that’s about it. </p>

<p>Markdown support has entered the mix since last I checked the app, and even better, it seems to fully understand MultiMarkdown<sup id="fnref:mmd"><a href="#fn:mmd" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, which is a huge win. Simple Markdown like headings, strong, italic, etc. are all handled correctly and shown while you’re editing the text. </p>

<p>The other <em>sine qua non</em> for a personal wiki that I had is inter-page links that just <em>appear</em> without any additional markup/markdown/whatever. When I type the name of another page I want it to be clickable. VoodooPad does that with aplomb. </p>

<p>So, as a personal wiki it’s doing what I want it to do. <em>Check</em>. </p>

<p>And there’s a lot more that I haven’t fully explored yet<sup id="fnref:investment"><a href="#fn:investment" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, like in-app scripting in Python, JSTalk, Ruby, shell, etc. and other potentially useful things like tagging, collections, built-in todo list collection…it’s basically the kitchen sink. </p>

<p>But there’s one huge dark spot: the iOS version of the app. It’s definitely been lacking in love or attention for years now. It’s not iOS 7-compiled, and most of the UI looks more like iOS 4. It doesn’t seem to open my main document, and it has separate editing/reading modes, thus getting rid of the main good thing I see in the desktop version. But, again, Plausible promises that improvments are coming. Which leads us to the second point: Trusting the company.</p>

<h2 id="trusting-plausible-labs">Trusting Plausible Labs</h2>

<p>This is where I have a bigger problem. It’s not that I think they’re incompetent, or lazy, or bad developers or anything. Just as I believe Gus knew when to get out of VoodooPad, I also believe that he didn’t hand it over to someone who would mess it up. But it’s not their baby. </p>

<p>I’m not saying I think they’ll let it languish, but they need to know that now is a very sensitive period for the product. They shouldn’t rush any bug fixes or new features just for the sake of putting out a new version, but semi-regular updates on the blog about how the work is coming, some notification that they <em>are</em> working on it would go a long way to build confidence.<sup id="fnref:clockwork"><a href="#fn:clockwork" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>That said, I’m going to <em>Invest</em>-with-a-capital-I in VoodooPad. And I great hopes of seeing Plausible Labs do great things with it. I just hope we don’t have to wait too long. </p>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:password">
      <p>Which means I bought it a <em>long freaking time ago</em>, because all of my software licenses have been stored in <a href="https://agilebits.com/onepassword">1Password</a> for years.<a href="#fnref:password" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:mmd">
      <p>Meaning: I threw <a href="http://fletcherpenney.net/">Fletcher T. Penny</a>’s <a href="http://multimarkdown.com/">MultiMarkdown</a> sample document into VoodooPad and it renders the entire thing correctly, right down to the header metadata and <a href="http://www.mathjax.org/">MathJAX</a> rendering. <a href="#fnref:mmd" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:investment">
      <p>Things that will have to wait until this app hits the Investment phase. <a href="#fnref:investment" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:clockwork">
      <p>Gaslamp Games has handled this brilliantly with their upcoming game <a href="http://clockworkempires.com/">Clockwork Empires</a>. They write weekly blog posts about the state of the game, things that include both the progress they’re making, and even better, <a href="http://www.gaslampgames.com/2013/08/28/programmer-rage/">the problems they’re having</a> (that last link is the best of all possible programming blog posts. Read it. Love it. Try not to laugh too hard. <a href="#fnref:clockwork" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fluency]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/30/fluency/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-30T08:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/30/fluency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 1998 I served an <a href="http://mormon.org/values/missionary-work">LDS Mission</a> to the Philippines. Those of you who are familiar with how LDS missionaries operate know the drill: you spend ten weeks learning the language in a classroom setting and then you get sent out with a more experienced missionary to try it on your own. And anyone who has ever tried to speak a language they’ve only heard in a classroom setting knows what comes next: you spend a lot of time staring at people who speak a language you thought you were pretty good at, and you have no idea what they’re saying. </p>

<p>So I set myself some goals. I wanted to laugh at a Tagalog joke, because I actually understood it. I wanted to get my accent to be less terrible<sup id="fnref:accent"><a href="#fn:accent" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and I wanted to actually think in Tagalog. These were little stepping stones I set for myself, goals I was trying to reach to show that I was actually gaining some actual fluency in the language. </p>

<p><span class="pullquote-right" data-pullquote="&#8220;Kaya ko ito!&#8221;">
And then, one night a few months after I landed in Manila I had a thought, just three words that came to me as I was walking across the town square: “Kaya ko ito!” That was it. In English<sup id="fnref:sorta"><a href="#fn:sorta" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> it’s “I can do this”.  But that’s not the point. The point was that I had the thought <em>in Tagalog</em> instead of having it in English and translating it. I had a long way to go, but it was clear that something was happening, and I was learning something. Since then that thought has come back to me from time to time when I’m trying to do something difficult. I’ll start in one something, bang my head against the wall for a while, and all of a sudden there will be a moment of clarity, a brief glimpse of the summit after the first day’s climb, and the words “Kaya ko ito” will come back into my head. I can do this.
</span></p>

<p>One of those difficult things has been learning vim. While I’ve been teaching myself to use it<sup id="fnref:painlessplug"><a href="#fn:painlessplug" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> I’ve had a lot of moments where it just seemed too hard, too useless, and I had to set myself some goals. They were simpler goals, things like “don’t lose half a file and have to restore it from my git backups again today”, and then more useful goals, like “actually use the search and replace engine,” followed shortly by “actually use vim’s regex engine without the <code>very magic</code> flag”. Litte steps to show that I was making progress. </p>

<p>And one day, just a little while ago, I had a simple task ahead of me: remove the last three arguments from a function declaration. Without really thinking about it I got my cursor inside the parentheses and since my cursor was just before the closing paren I typed</p>

<pre><code>d3F,
</code></pre>

<p>And that was it. In English<sup id="fnref:kinda"><a href="#fn:kinda" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> it’s “delete back through the third comma before the cursor”. But that’s not the point. The point is that I just <em>did</em> it, without looking at a cheat sheet, without using help, without standing there for two minutes trying to figure out how to do what I knew I wanted to do. It was the “Kaya kong ito” moment all over again. I know I’ve still got a lot of vim to learn, but it’s clear that something is happening, and I’m learning something.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:accent">
      <p>According a couple of people who knew me early in my mission I was attempting to speak Tagalog with a British accent. Given the fact that I grew up in Boise, Idaho I can only imagine how terrible that sounded.<a href="#fnref:accent" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:sorta">
      <p>More or less. It’s not grammatically perfect, but it’s close enough that people would have understood what I meant.<a href="#fnref:sorta" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:painlessplug">
      <p>and <a href="http://leanpub.com/painless_vim">writing a book</a> about using vim.<a href="#fnref:painlessplug" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:kinda">
      <p>More or less. I’m sure there’s a better way to do this, and probably a better way to explain it, but it’s close enough that vim understood what I meant.<a href="#fnref:kinda" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not During, But Due To NaNoWriMo]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/05/not-during-but-due-to-nanowrimo/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-05T10:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/05/not-during-but-due-to-nanowrimo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year marks my sixth year participating in <a href="http://nanowrimo.org/">NaNoWriMo</a>, and I’ve started wondering if there was really a <em>point</em> to writing a “novel” in a single month. Especially since I haven’t really developed any of them beyond the rough draft I wrote in November. </p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://natedickson.com/images/nano_win.png" title="National Novel Writing Month Winner" alt="National Novel Writing Month Winner" /> So, I “won” again this year, writing a book that I have absolutely no desire to pursue further. Which has made me wonder if I’m doing it wrong or if I need to maybe just give up on NaNoWriMo because it’s not helping me grow as a “real” writer. But then I realized something.</p>

<p>I never would have written <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em> if I hadn’t been taking part of NaNoWriMo every year. <em>Painless Vim</em> isn’t a novel, it’s not a wild flight of fancy that I pounded out in a month.<sup id="fnref:supposed"><a href="#fn:supposed" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  But there are a lot of things I learned from NaNoWriMo that made it possible for me to write <em>Painless Vim</em>. Some of the most important are: </p>

<ol>
  <li>Write every day. This is the first and only secret of writing, of course. </li>
  <li>Write your first draft like nobody is going to read it, because nobody <em>is</em> going to read it. You’ll revise it into something better. </li>
  <li>Write for yourself. There are others out there who are in the same place as you, and they’ll appreciate what you’ve written. </li>
  <li>Use Scrivener. <a href="http://www.favoritethingever.com/2010/10/scrivener/">I absolutely <em>love</em> Scrivener</a>, and six years of NaNo’ing has made it as comfortable as a well-worn pair of blue jeans for me. If I get up the energy I’ll write a post about how my Scrivener workflow looks one of these days. </li>
</ol>

<p>Now, I’m not saying that I’m the world’s best author. But I wrote a book and put it out there where people can buy it, which is something that never would have happened if it hadn’t been for National Novel Writing Month. And that’s enough to keep me coming back year after year.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:supposed">
      <p>It’s a tutorial book that was only <em>supposed</em> to take a month and has so far taken me about six.<a href="#fnref:supposed" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excerpt from Pacifica]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/01/excerpt-from-pacifica/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T07:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/01/excerpt-from-pacifica</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the best study of my main character, the one that I think most accurately captures who she thinks she is. </p>

<hr />

<p>The roadway sparkles and flows with light, a jeweled strand across the dark landscape. Cylee sat far up on a hill, the fresh, wild wind blowing her hair back. </p>

<p>She used to live in this place, this quiet, dark, outdoor world. Back before Pacifica, before the war…</p>

<p>The strings of lights eventually merge into the cities, connecting the nets of lights that represent civilization, mankind’s crowning jewels shining in the dark. And once you’re caught in that net it can feel like there’s nothing else, no other way to live. You can learn to depend on the Network, constant wireless streams of information flowing into and out of you at all times. You can learn to read the streets as you read the trees, feel the way the social wind is blowing just as you used to know how to read the fitful pre-dawn breezes. </p>

<p>And, in truth, Cylee was caught by that net. If she stayed out here for a few days or weeks her Spine would shut down and go from being an Augmentation to being thirty pounds of stiff dead metal. She’d be essentially blinded and deafened, her limbs left to their own strength. Even now she was half blind, her Spine out of range of the Network and therefore unable to give her the kind of information that made up the background noise of her daily life. Granted, she could still see every living, warm blooded thing that moved in the darkness, every rabbit, every bat, every bird was a blip on her augmented vision, their insane heart rates pounding like miniature thunder in her ears. </p>

<p>But she used to track them unaided. Used to be able to sense the movement of creatures that were string to remain hidden. She could feel the twitch in the grass that didn’t <em>quite</em> match the way the wind was moving. And she would raise her bow quietly, wait for the next movement…and…with a soft twang she would have breakfast.</p>

<p>Out of a sense of irony and frustration she considered raising her flechette thrower and pinning that rabbit to the ground, letting her Spine handle the fine details of getting her hand in the right position, but she stopped, realized she didn’t need the meat, and shouldn’t waste it. Pacifica had made her a perfect soldier, but it hadn’t entirely removed the true hunter she had been. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing With My Head In The Sand]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/11/11/writing-with-my-head-in-the-sand/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-11T15:09:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/11/11/writing-with-my-head-in-the-sand</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a saying about marriage that you should find a spouse with your eyes wide open and stay with a spouse with your eyes half shut.<sup id="fnref:source"><a href="#fn:source" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I’ve found this to be helpful advice about more than just marriage; when I buy a new computer I spend months reading reviews and write ups on the all the components involved and scouring the world for the best prices. Once I buy my components I all but block those sites on my browser; I don’t <em>want</em> to know that a brand new video card came out the same day my suddenly obsolete one arrives at my door. I just want to be happy with what I bought.</p>

<p>And, in an odd way it’s turning out to be true about writing <em><a href="http://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em>. There are two books and a few websites that I used quite a bit while I was starting to learn vim, they are somehow on my “okay” list. But any site or book I haven’t read yet is now <em>the enemy</em>, because I’m afraid they’re all better than the book I’m writing and I’ll have to die now. There are (at least) <a href="https://leanpub.com/VimLikeAPro">two</a> <a href="https://leanpub.com/learnvimscriptthehardway">other</a> vim books already on Leanpub.com; I can’t look at them too directly lest I discover the only thing my book has that the don’t is a whimsical cover. </p>

<p>And, of course, what does it matter? If other books are better that’s fine; I can hope that there are some people out there who will get what they need out of my little book. So I’m keeping my head in the sand a little bit. Some day I’ll be done writing <em>Painless Vim</em> and I’ll be able to read other people’s vim books.</p>

<p>There’s no real point here; just a little note about how my mind seems to work when I’m mid-book like this.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:source">
      <p>I can’t find the source for this, and I’m sorry. So let’s just pretend its common knowledge.<a href="#fnref:source" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My NaNoWriMo Cover for This Year]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/10/31/my-nanowrimo-cover-for-this-year/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-31T11:34:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/10/31/my-nanowrimo-cover-for-this-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/pacifica_cover.jpg" width="250" title="Pacifica Cover" />
This is a super-short post to show off what I&rsquo;m going to be working on for <a href="http://nanowrimo.org">NaNoWriMo</a> this year. </p>

<p>I know that <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim/">Painless Vim</a></em> isn&rsquo;t finished yet, although it&rsquo;s very close, and basically all I&rsquo;m doing is a little bit of cleanup and formatting. If you&rsquo;ve been waiting with baited breath for <em>Painless Vim</em> to be finished fear not! I will still be working on the Little Vim Book that Could during the month of November. In fact, my goal is to have it completely finished. By December 1st, even while I&rsquo;m &ldquo;winning&rdquo; NaNoWriMo for the sixth straight year. </p>

<p>In previous years I&rsquo;ve been doing graduate level classes, having babies<sup id="fnref:babies"><a href="#fn:babies" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and changing jobs during NaNoWriMo, and I&rsquo;ve always found time to make it work. What&rsquo;s more, the impetus it gives me tends to help me get more done in the rest of my life as well. The saying about giving work to busy people still holds true. If I turn myself into a busy person I tend to be more capable overall. Until I freak out and melt down, of course. So I guess there&rsquo;s still something to be said for balance. </p>

<h2 id="more-about-pacifica">More About Pacifica</h2>

<p>Which is all very nice, but you may possibly be interested in the book cover I&rsquo;m showing off here. You&rsquo;ve got questions, no doubt. Questions like &ldquo;What&rsquo;s it about?&rdquo; &ldquo;Who designed your cover?&rdquo; &ldquo;Would you be willing to let me redesign your cover, because it&rsquo;s pretty bad?&rdquo; </p>

<p>The answers are &ldquo;I&rsquo;ll tell you in a minute&rdquo;, &ldquo;I did in about two hours using Pixelmator&rdquo;, and &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; in that order. I like playing with Pixelmator, but I&rsquo;m not super great with it, and if there&rsquo;s a graphic designer out there who wants to take a second pass at this I&rsquo;d be happy to let you. </p>

<p>The book is my first foray into cyberpunk. It&rsquo;s a near-future look at what&rsquo;s its like to be on the losing side of a war for independence, and how to keep your pride even when you&rsquo;ve got nothing left to be proud of. </p>

<p>If I remember (and have time) I&rsquo;ll probably post excerpts through the month. Wether or not I actually develop <em>Pacifica</em> after November remains to be seen, but if I&rsquo;ve learned anything from five successful NaNo&rsquo;s its that even writing an ultimately wasted story isn&rsquo;t wasted effort. I&rsquo;ve learned something from every book I&rsquo;ve written.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:babies">
      <p>Well, not me <em>personally</em>. <a href="#fnref:babies" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using nvALT as a Personal Wiki]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/09/17/using-nvalt-as-a-personal-wiki/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T06:37:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/09/17/using-nvalt-as-a-personal-wiki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/nvALT.png" title="nvALT icon" />
One of the best things about <a href="http://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/">nvALT</a> is that it gives you a lot of tools you can use with little to no friction. You can use tags, or not, you can store your files in dropbox as individual markdown files, or you can keep them all in a single database<sup id="fnref:database"><a href="#fn:database" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. It&rsquo;s all up to you. It&rsquo;s very liberal about how you use its powers.</p>

<p>Which means I missed one.</p>

<p>Up until now I&rsquo;ve been using nvALT as my repository of code and notes on projects, useful tips and hints and things that I tend to forget. You know, all the stuff that makes nvALT great. The praises of nvALT have already been sung, and sung better than I will sing them here. But here&rsquo;s what I just discovered: the inter-note linking feature. </p>

<p><strong>OH. MAN.</strong></p>

<p>Okay, those of you who already knew about this can just go ahead and laugh at me. But for those of you who haven&rsquo;t discovered this yet, it&rsquo;s very very simple and powerful. Just wrap the name of another note in <code>[[double brackets]]</code> and you have a link to that note. What&rsquo;s more, once you open the double brackets you can start typing the name of a file and nvALT will autocomplete it for you.</p>

<p>With this addition, nvALT has supplanted VoodooPad, EverNote, and my <a href="https://github.com/PogiNate/SublimeWiki">own home-brew Sublime Text Wiki system</a>. Not only is it more flexible, but it also has one of the best built-in markdown previews ever. </p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:database">
      <p>Pro Tip: store them as separate files in Dropbox!<a href="#fnref:database" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small World on the iPad Updated!]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/09/12/small-world-on-the-ipad-updated/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T10:04:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/09/12/small-world-on-the-ipad-updated</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/SW2-icon.jpg" title="&#34;Small World 2 App Icon&#34;" alt="&#34;Small World 2 App Icon&#34;" />
Just a quick post to happily note that <a href="http://www.daysofwonder.com">Days of Wonder</a> has finally updated their <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/small-world-for-ipad/id364165557?mt=8">Small World app</a> on the iPad. Small World was the first game I bought on the original iPad, and it&rsquo;s been sadly neglected for a quite a while. </p>

<p>But it&rsquo;s back in business now! It&rsquo;s beautifully, fully retina, has new content (available through an in app purchase), and now lets you play with up to five people via pass &amp; play, or you can have the one on one experience that you&rsquo;re used to from the original version. I&rsquo;ve always loved Days Of Wonder&rsquo;s games, and they continue to do a great job bringing them to the iPad. Thanks guys!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Case for Board Games on Tablets]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/09/03/the-case-for-board-games-on-tablets/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-03T08:45:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/09/03/the-case-for-board-games-on-tablets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My wife and I love board games. So it’s only natural that our kids will love them as well. And that’s <em>awesome</em>. But since all of our kids are under nine years old playing games with them can be a bit of a headache, because they don’t really have a sense of how losing one tiny little piece can ruin a sixty dollar game, and pieces are really small and easily lost. </p>

<p>Enter the iPad. I bought the tablet version of SmallWorld back when I had a 1st Gen iPad, and while it’s fun, at the time my wife and I only used it to pass time when we were waiting for a table at a restauraunt or whatever. Since then I have also picked up Ticket to Ride and Forbidden Island, and my kids and I spent most of this weekend playing all three games over and over and <em>over</em> again, as kids are wont to do. </p>

<p>And it was a pretty amazing experience. I still love my “real” board games, for a number of reasons: the artwork is bigger, you get a tactile sense of what you’re doing, the experience is more immersive, and you can see the board from more than two feet away, etc. etc. </p>

<p>But when you’re playing with a passel of excitable kiddos there’s a lot to be said for keeping the iPad firmly in my hands as they all take their turns, get excited by the (usually quite minimal) resulting animations, and go dance around the room for a while. When the game is over I just close the cover and the game is packed up, no cleanup required. </p>

<p>A quick note about animations: If you’re doing a straight up port of your board game don’t try to make it a full-on video game. Take a look at <em>Ticket to Ride</em> by Days of Wonder and stick to that level: make your graphics and chrome beautiful, but let’s keep it a board game.</p>

<p>The other advantage is price. Since all I’m getting is a pile o’ bytes I don’t have to pay for a bunch of die cut custom printed cardboard pieces, which usually translates into around a 75% savings or better. The companies usually have a lot of high-quality assets all ready for the games, since you can and should use the same art for the digital and analog versions, so the R&amp;D costs are apparently low enough to make it worth doing. </p>

<p>Of course, in my situation this generally means I’m buying a game 1.25 times instead of 2 times, but hey, it’s still a savings. </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Google]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/30/leaving-google/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T08:40:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/30/leaving-google</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Edward Snowden basically only verified what we had all already feared: The government is getting information about all of us behind our backs. The problem is that all this time Google has been promising that they’re doing a nice, open, transparent operation, letting us all know what they’re being asked for and what they’re actually giving, and now…well, I have a hard time believing them. </p>

<p>But it’s more than that. The old wisdom about eggs and numbers of baskets used to store them rings very true these days. Regardless of government requests<sup id="fnref:no_hide"><a href="#fn:no_hide" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, regardless of anything else, I’ve gradually become uncomfortable letting google moderate all aspects of my online life. </p>

<p>So I’m trying to move away from services that I’ve been using for  years. And the sad fact is that the alternatives just <em>aren’t</em> as good as the Google offerings. There’s no getting around it. But here’s what I’m using in my attempt at going Google-free:</p>

<h2 id="firefox">Firefox</h2>

<p>Back to the fox. Firefox was once a shining star of the future of the web and now it’s kind of like Safari: At least it’s not Internet Explorer. But it has plugins like AdBlock Plus <sup id="fnref:block_comments"><a href="#fn:block_comments" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> and <a href="http://www.abine.com/how-donottrackme-works/">Do Not Track Me</a>, both of which make it easier to keep anybody from following me around on the internet. Again, if they want to know where I go all day every day they can just <em>ask</em> me (or look at my <a href="https://pinboard.in/u:PogiNate">Pinboard</a>), but I’d like them to have the decency to ask.</p>

<h2 id="duckduckgo">DuckDuckGo</h2>

<p><a href="https://duckduckgo.com/">DDG</a> is a great search engine for people who don’t want to be tracked. It stores exactly <em>nothing</em> about you, meaning your searches aren’t tailored or customized based on your past search history. They have a great summary of <a href="http://donttrack.us/">why this is a good thing</a> linked to their home page.</p>

<p>The downside is that, well, you’re not getting customized results, which means that sometimes you have to dig a few pages down to get the content you really want. But the results are quite good and getting better daily. </p>

<h2 id="gmail">Gmail…</h2>

<p>This is the one that’s going to be difficult. Gmail is the king of free email, bar none. To get anywhere close to the feature set that gmail provides is going to require paying for email, and if I’m going to do that I’d like to pay for really <em>really</em> secure email. So I’m still looking for a good replacement. </p>

<p>At first I was put off by the really small quotas most email providers give you. I mean, Gmail is up to 15GB free! A lot of them charge you for anything over 1GB! <strong>GASP!!</strong></p>

<p>But then I looked at my actual usage. I’ve had my gmail account for around 7 years, and I’ve used about .56GB. Yep. Half a gig.<sup id="fnref:inboxZero"><a href="#fn:inboxZero" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> So I’m probably okay on that front. Based on that I’m looking at a few options:</p>

<p>-<strong><a href="http://lavabit.com/index.html">Lavabit</a></strong> is an email provider who values security, security, security. For $8 a year you get 1GB of storage <sup id="fnref:upgrade"><a href="#fn:upgrade" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> and <a href="http://lavabit.com/secure.html">totally encrypted email</a>. The price is good, and as I’ve said, I think I can swing a single gigabyte. 
- <strong><a href="https://www.hushmail.com/services/hushmail/features/">Hushmail</a></strong> Gives you PGP signed email…if you are sending to people who know how to open PGP encrypted email. They charge $34.99/year for 1GB of storage, but if you want to use a desktop email client via POP/IMAP you will have to go up to $49.98/year for some reason. 
- <strong><a href="https://www.fastmail.fm/signup/personal.html">FastMail</a></strong> is owned by <a href="http://www.opera.com/">Opera</a> and is somewhere between Lavabit and Hushmail: it’s $19.95/year for 1GB, no mention of encryption on the server, but fully secure communication between client and server, and no (known) agreement with the NSA. </p>

<h2 id="duckduckgo-xmpp">DuckDuckGo XMPP</h2>

<p>Apparently Google is ending support for the XMPP protocol for Gtalk, which makes it a much less useful chat system. Which is a shame, because a lot of my coworkers use it almost exclusively. </p>

<p>But DuckDuckGo is there for you in this arena as well. They provide <a href="https://dukgo.com/blog/xmpp-services-at-duckduckgo">an XMPP server </a>that is much less Stalker-ish than GTalk, and also isn’t being deprecated in favor of closed protocols.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Google has done a good job of making themselves incredibly useful, and they make some very good apps. In the end it’s a question of how much you’re willing to give them in exchange for those services. I’d still like to believe that Google hasn’t totally abandoned their “Don’t Be Evil” mantra, but it’s still a good idea to check out the competition.  </p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:no_hide">
      <p>I really don’t have anything to hide. If the NSA wants to steal my dominos pizza coupons they’re welcome to them. But I would like them to <em>ask</em> first.<a href="#fnref:no_hide" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:block_comments">
      <p>Which I mostly use to hide comment sections on web pages.<a href="#fnref:block_comments" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:inboxZero">
      <p>Inbox Zero, yo. <a href="#fnref:inboxZero" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:upgrade">
      <p>Upgradable to 8GB for $16/year<a href="#fnref:upgrade" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Slicereader to be a Better Writer]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/17/using-slicereader-to-be-a-better-writer/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-17T15:02:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/17/using-slicereader-to-be-a-better-writer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://natedickson.com/assets/images/Slicereader.jpg" title="&#34;The Slicereader Icon&#34;" alt="&#34;The Slicereader Icon&#34;" />
Working on <a href="http://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a> has been an education for me, and not just about vim. I&rsquo;ve  been working on developing a writing/editing loop that is more sustainable than <a href="http://nanowrimo.org">NaNoWriMo</a>&rsquo;s joyous abandon, so that I&rsquo;ll actually do some editing. While I enjoy working quickly and just getting things out there in front of people, there&rsquo;s a problem with that model: not only am I terrible typist, I also write some terrible first drafts.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0385480016/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0385480016&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=httpnatedicco-20">Anne Lamott</a> would say that&rsquo;s okay; and I agree with her. But the problem is that I&rsquo;m also <em>really bad</em> at revising. Part of my problem is that I&rsquo;m a very good speed reader, which really just means that I&rsquo;m good at skimming over what I consider to be fluff and finding what I consider to be the point of the text in front of me. Good for getting through things quickly, bad for finding mistakes in my own text. </p>

<p>So I needed a way to force myself to slow down and actually look at the words. Not surprisingly it was <a href="http://brettterpstra.com/2013/06/30/mac-app-review-slicereader/">Brett Terpstra</a> that clued me into this simple little &ldquo;one thing well&rdquo; app. With <a href="http://mthr.me/slicereader/">Slicereader</a> I just paste whatever chapter I&rsquo;m working on into the app, and it converts all of my Markdown into nicely formatted text<sup id="fnref:mostly"><a href="#fn:mostly" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and only shows me one paragraph at a time. Meaning I have to actually <em>read</em> that paragraph all by itself. Meaning I have to view it as a single entity, without resting on what came before or after it. Meaning I end up editing <em>every</em> paragraph instantly and repeatedly, reloading the text and seeing how my new changes stand up. </p>

<p>Slicereader is almost disturbingly focused on what it sets out to do: there are no fancy options to twiddle, no settings, no font pickers. You can choose daytime or nighttime mode. But when I need some  help focusing on my editing, having all those choices taken from me is definitely a good thing.</p>

<p>And yes, I&rsquo;ve run this article through Slicereader as well. </p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:mostly">
      <p>Mostly. It only handles Gruber markdown, meaning no footnotes, etc.<a href="#fnref:mostly" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Books!]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/11/free-books/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-11T09:11:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/11/free-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I recently put a coupon up on <a href="https://twitter.com/poginate">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://alpha.app.net/poginate">App.net</a> offering ten people the opportunity to get a free copy of my book <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em>, which is still very much in <strong>alpha</strong>. But I figured attracting a few extra readers couldn’t do anything but help. </p>

<p>And in next to no time all ten free copies were gone, which is awesome. I’m not so much about the money on this one, I’m just enjoying writing it and really want to see it published and hopefully help a few people. </p>

<p>Anyway, it occurred to me that I hadn’t offered free copies to any of my faithful blog followers! So, here’s the deal: here’s another coupon code, also good for the first 10, nah, let’s say 20 people, but the condition is that I <em>really</em> would like any feedback you have about the book, even in this early state. Okay, ready? Here’s the skinny:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Go to <a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">https://leanpub.com/painless_vim</a></li>
  <li>buy the book using the coupon code <strong>Blog20</strong>. <sup id="fnref:paymor"><a href="#fn:paymor" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
  <li>Give me some awesome and useful feedback on the book either through the Leanpub site, as a comment on this site. Or ping me on <a href="https://twitter.com/poginate">Twitter</a>/<a href="https://alpha.app.net/poginate">App.net</a> with the hashtag #PainlessVim. However you get the feedback to me I will definitely take it into consideration and use it to improve the book.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:paymor">
      <p>And if you <em>want</em> to pay more than nothing I won’t stop you! Seriously! I’d be fine with it!<a href="#fnref:paymor" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Scrivener to Leanpub in One Step]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/30/from-scrivener-to-leanpub-in-one-step/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-30T00:46:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/30/from-scrivener-to-leanpub-in-one-step</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m working on <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em> in <a href="www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php">Scrivener</a>, because I love its organizational capabilities <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> …or have I mentioned my love of Scrivener before? (yes)</p>

<p>The problem arises when I want to push my text to <a href="https://leanpub.com">Leanpub</a>. Scrivener has two very good ways to get your text out of Scriv into the world: you can <em>export</em> each text as a file, or you can <em>compile</em> it into a single document ready to send off to a printer. They’ve both got their pros and cons, but to really understand them we need a brief detour into how publishing on Leanpub works:</p>

<h3 id="brief-detour-into-how-publishing-on-leanpub-works">Brief Detour Into How Publishing on Leanpub Works</h3>

<p>to publish your text on Leanpub you put all your chapters or whatever into individual <code>.txt</code> files, which you put into a special Dropbox folder called something like <code>~/Dropbox/name_of_book/manuscript/</code>. then you include a file called <code>Book.txt</code> to tell Leanpub what order the text files should be in when the book is put together. You can also create a <code>Sample.txt</code> file that tells Leanpub which text files to put into a free sample that potential buyers can download, and  a <code>Preview.txt</code> file that lets you just render a specific part of the book to make sure the formatting looks the way you want it. Okay, that’s your brief tutorial on Leanpub.</p>

<p>So, back to getting text out of Scrivener into this folder.</p>

<p>The compile option seems like a great choice at first: it creates a single text file made up of all the text in your document, formatted however you like, and once you’ve created your compile settings it’s a single click operation. </p>

<p>The problem is with the Sample and Preview options. Since your text is all in a single file you can’t pick and choose individual parts of the text to give away for free. You could have two separate compile settings, but that seems very labor intensive.</p>

<p>So, the “export” option is the way to go, right? Every text section in your Scrivener project is exported as a single text file, just like Leanpub wants, you can create <code>Sample.txt</code> and <code>Preview.txt</code> files and everything is good. </p>

<p>Well, one problem. Let’s say  you’ve got your book laid out in Folders instead of as just a list of text files in Scrivener. When it exports your book it creates the full file structure:</p>

<pre><code>Painless Vim
| 
+- Part I
|	|
|	+- Chapter 1.txt
|	+- Chapter2.txt
+- Part II
	|
	+- Chapter 3.txt	 
</code></pre>

<p>And so forth. You get the picture. This is a problem because Leanpub doesn’t do subfolders; you need all the files to be in the root of the <code>manuscript/</code> directory. So, after doing an export from Scrivener I needed a way to flatten out the file system.</p>

<h3 id="enter-automator">Enter Automator</h3>

<p>Here’s the fun part. I could have written a ruby script to go through the exported file and copy all the <code>.txt</code> files to the <code>manuscript</code> folder. But that would have taken <em>minutes</em>. Like, <em>dozens</em> of them. So I decided to once again let Automator have a crack at it.</p>

<p>And it was <strong>easy</strong>. Automator has gotten a lot more useful since last I played with it<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, with things like variables and other things you’d expect from a real scripting environment. What’s more, I was able to set up my workflow as a “folder action”, watching the <code>~/Documents/Painless/</code> folder which I created specifically for this purpose. Now I just tell Scrivener to export into that directory and Automator takes it from there. </p>

<p>The Automator workflow I set up is dead simple:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Save the name of whatever just appeared in <code>Painless</code> in a variable called <code>New Folder</code> <sup id="fnref:names"><a href="#fn:names" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> .</li>
  <li>Get everything in the new folder, recursively</li>
  <li>Filter that list by file extension (in this case, we only want .txt files)</li>
  <li>Copy all those text files to <code>~/Dropbox/painless_vim/manuscript/</code>, overwriting any existing files.</li>
  <li>Delete whatever is stored in <code>incoming</code>. </li>
</ol>

<p>And there you have it. The last step is just to make the export from Scrivener one step shorter, because it doesn’t have to ask if you want to overwrite your last export.</p>

<p>There are a lot of advantages to this setup. I can now export a single text file or folder instead of the entire project, and just that file will get overwritten. For single file exports this is nearly instantaneous, opposed to the <em>three whole seconds</em> it takes to export my entire project.  I  can also have <em>all</em> my files, including my <code>Book.txt, Sample.txt</code> and <code>Preview.txt</code> managed in Scrivener, which I couldn’t do if I were doing the Compile option. </p>

<p>Over all I’m very pleased with this workflow. It’s taken one of the pain points out of writing <em>Painless Vim</em>. </p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Okay, I know it seems odd that I’m writing a book called <em>Painless Vim</em> and here I am admitting that I’m using a completely different editor to write it. What’s the deal here? The deal is that it’s really easy to copy and paste text around between editors (especially using Hog Bay’s <a href="http://www.hogbaysoftware.com/products/quickcursor">QuickCursor</a>, but that’s an entirely different footnote), and while I do most of the actual writing in vim, I keep the text files in Scrivener for reasons that will be expounded upon in a future blog post.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>at least four years ago<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:names">
      <p>Let’s not make fun of bad variable names here, Thank you so much.<a href="#fnref:names" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Painless Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/22/introducing-painless-vim/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-22T12:47:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/22/introducing-painless-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://natedickson.com/images/painless_cover.png" title="Painless Vim Cover" />
I&rsquo;m excited to announce the availability of <em>Painless Vim</em>, my new (indeed, still in progress) book on the ever powerful vim editor! While the book is still in progress, you can pick up a copy at <a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Leanpub</a> right now and make suggestions to help guide the development of this book. I&rsquo;m very impressed by the Leanpub system, allowing authors to write their books out in the open and get feedback along the way. </p>

<h2 id="why-another-vim-tutorial">Why Another Vim Tutorial?</h2>

<p>I started thinking about writing this book when I realized I <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/2010/07/29/everyone-who-tried-to-convince-me-to-use-vim-was-wrong/">wasn&rsquo;t the only developer</a> who has tried to use vim and was put off by the vast majority of vim training available. Vim is really very developer friendly, but a lot of the teaching resources for vim are anything but. My goal is to take the best of what I have picked up in my journey to vim and present it in a way that helps other people get over the initial hurdle and into the good parts of the editor.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be writing quite a bit about the development process of the book and the workflow involved. Watch this space!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Terrible Time Travel Concept for a Cheesy Sci-fi Movie]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/20/terrible-time-travel-concept-for-a-cheesy-sci-fi-movie/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T15:35:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/20/terrible-time-travel-concept-for-a-cheesy-sci-fi-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>NOTE</strong>: I’m presenting this as a <em>movie plot</em>, not <em>actual science</em>. I’m a programmer, not a physicist. I’m fully aware that I have no idea how physics works and that everything below is probably complete nonsense. Which is why it would be perfect for Hollywood. Okay, carry on. </p>

<p>So, here’s the premise: Light moves at, well, light speed. The closer you get to moving at light speed, the slower subjective time moves. Which means that for light, time doesn’t move <em>at all</em>. Which is probably part of why it’s both photons (particles) and light waves (energy); if there’s no time there is no significant difference between the two.<sup id="fnref:relax"><a href="#fn:relax" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Okay, so here’s the sci-fi movie upshot of all this, using a lot of tech wizardry that makes very little sense: A scientist discovers a way to entangle photons, so that when you send a concentrated beam of photons out the state of each emitted photon is mirrored in a trapped photon. (Remember: this is <strong>movie science</strong>, not real science) the kicker is that the state of the emitted photon is identical to the trapped photon until it hits something, which is when it starts experiencing non-light-speed time again, and is <em>also</em> useful because light, moving at light speed doesn’t experience subjective time at all, so the moment when it strikes something, even if that is far in the (observer’s subjective) future, is reflected in the trapped photon <em>instantly</em>. By reading the state of your trapped photons, you can observe events in more-or-less real time by using a really powerful computer, probably with code scrolling across its screen at all times.</p>

<p>Now we mix in the science magic that non-scientific people call “quantum” and we assume that you can interpolate details about the surroundings of the emitted photon from its state when it strikes something and viola! You’ve invented a way to look forward in time. By bouncing the photon off of things at various distances from the earth (reflection doesn’t cause the photon to resolve its state because shut up) you can observe future conditions at various points in the future. And thus quasi-scientific movie magic is born. </p>

<p>From here you can do various things with explorations of the deterministic nature of the universe, either saying that everything remains the same no matter what you try to do to change them (essentially turning light into a sci-fi version of the Oracle at Delphi) or you can have the light beams show that individual changes can alter the course of history. Or for even more fun you can throw some vaguely understood concepts about the act of observation changing that which is observed and say that us spying on the future is itself changing the future. The fact that we’re also changing that future’s past only serves to further complicate the relationship between the two events. </p>

<p>And then, as the final twist (or material for the sequel) you can reveal that the future is using the same light beams to spy on <em>us</em>. </p>

<p>Any major movie studios wishing to do a plot treatment can leave a comment below. I’m reasonable.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:relax">
      <p>Before you actual physicsts go all crazy in the comments read the first paragraph again, and then chant the <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/MST3KMantra">MST3K mantra</a> until you feel better. <a href="#fnref:relax" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From The Desk of Captain Obvious: Tmuxinator vs. Scripted configurations]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/10/from-the-desk-of-captain-obvious-tmuxinator-vs-scripted-configurations/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-10T10:38:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/10/from-the-desk-of-captain-obvious-tmuxinator-vs-scripted-configurations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been using <a href="https://github.com/aziz/tmuxinator">Tmuxinator</a> for a while now to put together tmux sessions that I can run quickly and easily from the command line. I’ve even set up an <a href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/04/12/introducing-a-dot-k-a-dot-the-alias-manager/">AKA</a> shortcut, abbreviating <code>tmuxinator</code> to <code>tor</code>, making it much easier to create new scripted sessions. But recently I discovered an odd thing when I detached from a session created by tmuxinator: they don’t show up in my list of sessions when I run <code>tmux ls</code>. </p>

<p>So I played with it a bit more. I could run <code>tor config1</code> and get a session laid out according to configuration 1. I’d then detach and create a session by hand, and do the following:</p>

<pre><code>$ tmux new -s bar -d
$ tmux ls
bar: 1 windows (created Thu May 9 07:35:02) [160x39]
</code></pre>

<p>Well that’s odd. So I’d try </p>

<pre><code>tmux attach -t config1
</code></pre>

<p>and it would say it can’t find the session.  Out of curiosity (did I kill the session instead of just detaching?) I’d run </p>

<pre><code>tor config1
</code></pre>

<p>again, and I would be back in my already-running session.</p>

<p>Okay, most of you have already gotten here ahead of me. When you run Tmuxinator it’s issuing commands from ruby, not from your user session. The tmux process that ruby uses is a child process of ruby, not of your shell. This is fine if you create all your sessions from Tmuxinator, but if you start standing up impromptu sessions just because, or if you have decided to have tmux start whenever your terminal opens it means that your Tmuxinator sessions and your non-Tmuxinator sessions are on totally different servers, so you can’t use <code>&lt;prefix&gt;)</code> to switch between them.</p>

<p>So I decided to bite the bullet and move my Tmuxinator sessions over to independently executable scripts. It’s more steps, not quite as pretty, but the commands are all sensible, and now sessions I create using my scripts are visible on my “main” tmux server. And I’m free of one more external dependency, which is nice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buy Quality]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/06/buy-quality/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T12:54:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/06/buy-quality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have a <a href="http://www.timbuk2.com/tb2/">Timbuk2</a> bag that I purchased six years ago, when I got my first MacBook. Even though I only had a 13” <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:MacBook.jpg">black plastic MacBook</a> at the time, I got the 15” messenger bag because I figured the odds were pretty good that <em>someday</em> I would have a 15” MacBook Pro. </p>

<p><span class="pullquote-right" data-pullquote="But other than a bit of dirt the bag still looks pretty much as good as it did when I bought it."> 
The 13” MacBook is gone, one 15” MBP has come and gone and a new one now lives in the same pocket of the same messenger bag I picked up all those years ago. That bag has been through airports, camping trips, freezing terrible outdoor IT jobs in the dead of winter and hot terrible outdoor IT jobs in the dog days of summer. Now it’s pretty much relegated to hauling my computer back and forth to and from the office because I’ve left my IT days behind me.  But other than a bit of dirt the bag still looks pretty much as good as it did when I bought it. The seams are still tight and solid, the velcro still works, the material is still without any frayed or torn spots. The bag cost more than I could afford at the time<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but I’ve never regretted the decision.  I got something that was well made, and I’m grateful. 
</span> </p>

<p>So, not a big post, or a deep important mystery of life this time around, sorry. Not even a cool new tech toy to play with. My only real point is that if you do some research and find something worth investing in<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> you will be rewarded for it. </p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>In fact, it cost more than the second-hand MacBook it was purchased to carry<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Time or money; learning vim has been a huge investment of time for me, not so much on the financial side.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
