<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: VoodooPad | Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/categories/voodoopad/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-14T10:15:12-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://natedickson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trusting VoodooPad]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/01/13/trusting-voodoopad/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T11:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/01/13/trusting-voodoopad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/assets/images/vp_icon.png" title="‘VoodooPad Icon’ ‘The VoodooPad Icon’" >
I’ve <a href="http://www.favoritethingever.com/2010/10/scrivener/">mentioned before</a> that I go through three phases as I get used to a new program: <em>Inquiry</em>, <em>Inquisition</em> and <em>Investment</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <em>Inquiry</em> phase is the “does it do what I want it to do, without being irritating?” phase. Basically this is like a caveman poking a thing with a sharp stick, hiding behind a rock to see if it tries to bite him, then biting <em>it</em> to see if it’s worth eating.</p>

  <p>If a program gets past that, then comes the <em>Inquisition</em>: “Oh yeah, well can you handle <em>this</em>? What about <em>that</em>? And how do you like the <em>comfy chair</em>?”</p>

  <p>Anything that makes it past the Inquisition with any level of approval gets my <em>Investment</em>, the phase where I put the time into learning how to use the program to its fullest and really start using it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve put VoodooPad through the wringer before. Searching through my email reveals that I have a version 2 license<sup id="fnref:password"><a href="#fn:password" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. I liked the idea, the core of VoodooPad back then, but it never got past the Inquisition. I could see that it <em>wanted</em> to do things right, but we never <em>clicked</em>. </p>

<p>Still, when I got the email that VoodooPad had left its original home at Flying Meat I was kinda saddened. It may not have been my cup of tea, but it was still an amazing product and it’s cool in a way that is hard to put into words. Don’t get me wrong, I think Gus of Flying Meat made the right choice when he decided to <a href="http://www.flyingmeat.com/blog/archives/2013/11/a_new_home_for_voodoopad.html">sell VoodooPad</a>. If he doesn’t feel he can maintain it any more nobody would know better than he would. </p>

<p>The new owners at <a href="https://plausible.coop/">Plausible Labs</a> have promised to make it better and take great care of it, because they love VoodooPad and want to see it grow. That’s great news. </p>

<p>But can I trust it?</p>

<p>There’s two questions there: Can I trust Plausible Labs to keep making VoodooPad better, and can I trust VoodooPad to be good enough to deserve my investment?</p>

<p>For the record I’ve already purchased my license; so we’re not talking about <em>financial</em> investment. I’m talking about investing my time, which is far more valuable these days. (“oh, look at Mr. Moneybags!” Yeah, yeah, you know what I meant.)</p>

<p>So, second question first: Can I trust VoodooPad, the program, to be what I want it to be?</p>

<h2 id="trusting-the-program">Trusting the Program</h2>

<p>This is the bigger of the two questions. After all, if VoodooPad is good enough to use and invest in now it doesn’t need a lot of updates all the time. My beloved Scrivener gets (I would say) <em>Just enough</em> updates: Not every month, but every so often. And even if updates stopped tomorrow I would keep using it until it no longer worked on whatever Mac I was using in the far future. </p>

<p>So I’ve started the process. I would say I’m near the end of the Inquisition phase right now. And what I’ve found is hopeful. Coming to version 5 of VoodooPad from version 2 left me refreshingly free of preconceived notions about the program: I knew it was a “Personal Wiki” and that’s about it. </p>

<p>Markdown support has entered the mix since last I checked the app, and even better, it seems to fully understand MultiMarkdown<sup id="fnref:mmd"><a href="#fn:mmd" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, which is a huge win. Simple Markdown like headings, strong, italic, etc. are all handled correctly and shown while you’re editing the text. </p>

<p>The other <em>sine qua non</em> for a personal wiki that I had is inter-page links that just <em>appear</em> without any additional markup/markdown/whatever. When I type the name of another page I want it to be clickable. VoodooPad does that with aplomb. </p>

<p>So, as a personal wiki it’s doing what I want it to do. <em>Check</em>. </p>

<p>And there’s a lot more that I haven’t fully explored yet<sup id="fnref:investment"><a href="#fn:investment" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, like in-app scripting in Python, JSTalk, Ruby, shell, etc. and other potentially useful things like tagging, collections, built-in todo list collection…it’s basically the kitchen sink. </p>

<p>But there’s one huge dark spot: the iOS version of the app. It’s definitely been lacking in love or attention for years now. It’s not iOS 7-compiled, and most of the UI looks more like iOS 4. It doesn’t seem to open my main document, and it has separate editing/reading modes, thus getting rid of the main good thing I see in the desktop version. But, again, Plausible promises that improvments are coming. Which leads us to the second point: Trusting the company.</p>

<h2 id="trusting-plausible-labs">Trusting Plausible Labs</h2>

<p>This is where I have a bigger problem. It’s not that I think they’re incompetent, or lazy, or bad developers or anything. Just as I believe Gus knew when to get out of VoodooPad, I also believe that he didn’t hand it over to someone who would mess it up. But it’s not their baby. </p>

<p>I’m not saying I think they’ll let it languish, but they need to know that now is a very sensitive period for the product. They shouldn’t rush any bug fixes or new features just for the sake of putting out a new version, but semi-regular updates on the blog about how the work is coming, some notification that they <em>are</em> working on it would go a long way to build confidence.<sup id="fnref:clockwork"><a href="#fn:clockwork" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>That said, I’m going to <em>Invest</em>-with-a-capital-I in VoodooPad. And I great hopes of seeing Plausible Labs do great things with it. I just hope we don’t have to wait too long. </p>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:password">
      <p>Which means I bought it a <em>long freaking time ago</em>, because all of my software licenses have been stored in <a href="https://agilebits.com/onepassword">1Password</a> for years.<a href="#fnref:password" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:mmd">
      <p>Meaning: I threw <a href="http://fletcherpenney.net/">Fletcher T. Penny</a>’s <a href="http://multimarkdown.com/">MultiMarkdown</a> sample document into VoodooPad and it renders the entire thing correctly, right down to the header metadata and <a href="http://www.mathjax.org/">MathJAX</a> rendering. <a href="#fnref:mmd" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:investment">
      <p>Things that will have to wait until this app hits the Investment phase. <a href="#fnref:investment" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:clockwork">
      <p>Gaslamp Games has handled this brilliantly with their upcoming game <a href="http://clockworkempires.com/">Clockwork Empires</a>. They write weekly blog posts about the state of the game, things that include both the progress they’re making, and even better, <a href="http://www.gaslampgames.com/2013/08/28/programmer-rage/">the problems they’re having</a> (that last link is the best of all possible programming blog posts. Read it. Love it. Try not to laugh too hard. <a href="#fnref:clockwork" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
