<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: nerd fun | Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/categories/nerd-fun/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-17T15:34:23-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[tmux and Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/03/21/tmux-and-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-21T05:22:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/03/21/tmux-and-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Naturally, the first thing I did after getting Octopress up, running, and actually <em>deployed</em> to a real live server was set up a writing workflow that will make it easy to post to this blog. And by “easy”, I of course mean “weird and convoluted, but in a way that makes sense to me”. What else would I mean?</p>

<p>The first ingredient in my workflow is <a href="http://tmux.sourceforge.net/">tmux</a>. If you haven’t played with it yet you’ll find that  it’s a fast and easy way to access your project from multiple angles. You’ll have one terminal window open and in that one window you can be editing a file, keeping an eye on <code>top</code> and running your build tasks all at once, while a second tab has your development server running in it. I discovered tmux using Brian Hogan’s <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/bhtmux/tmux">amazing book</a> and haven’t looked back. </p>

<p>The second part of the recipe here is <a href="https://github.com/aziz/tmuxinator">tmuxinator</a>, a nice little ruby app that lets you set up tmux layouts in <code>YAML</code> instead of writing the commands out as actual tmux commands, like so:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/5212311.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>You can see I have <code>rake preview</code> and <code>top</code> running on a “background” tab, so I can preview the site, and <code>vim</code> running on the first tab with a couple of regular old <code>zsh</code> panes at the project root and at the <code>_posts</code> directory, so I can issue other commands to the system and use Marked.app to preview my posts, etc. etc.  </p>

<p>Obviously I haven’t been using this particular setup for all that long yet, but it’s got a lot of promise. I’m pleased with how it’s turning out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
