<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: painless vim | Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/categories/painless-vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-11T15:35:30-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing With My Head In The Sand]]></title>
    <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/11/11/writing-with-my-head-in-the-sand/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-11T15:09:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/11/11/writing-with-my-head-in-the-sand</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a saying about marriage that you should find a spouse with your eyes wide open and stay with a spouse with your eyes half shut.<sup id="fnref:source"><a href="#fn:source" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I’ve found this to be helpful advice about more than just marriage; when I buy a new computer I spend months reading reviews and write ups on the all the components involved and scouring the world for the best prices. Once I buy my components I all but block those sites on my browser; I don’t <em>want</em> to know that a brand new video card came out the same day my suddenly obsolete one arrives at my door. I just want to be happy with what I bought.</p>

<p>And, in an odd way it’s turning out to be true about writing <em><a href="http://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em>. There are two books and a few websites that I used quite a bit while I was starting to learn vim, they are somehow on my “okay” list. But any site or book I haven’t read yet is now <em>the enemy</em>, because I’m afraid they’re all better than the book I’m writing and I’ll have to die now. There are (at least) <a href="https://leanpub.com/VimLikeAPro">two</a> <a href="https://leanpub.com/learnvimscriptthehardway">other</a> vim books already on Leanpub.com; I can’t look at them too directly lest I discover the only thing my book has that the don’t is a whimsical cover. </p>

<p>And, of course, what does it matter? If other books are better that’s fine; I can hope that there are some people out there who will get what they need out of my little book. So I’m keeping my head in the sand a little bit. Some day I’ll be done writing <em>Painless Vim</em> and I’ll be able to read other people’s vim books.</p>

<p>There’s no real point here; just a little note about how my mind seems to work when I’m mid-book like this.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:source">
      <p>I can’t find the source for this, and I’m sorry. So let’s just pretend its common knowledge.<a href="#fnref:source" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Books!]]></title>
    <link href="http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/07/11/free-books/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-11T09:11:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://PogiNate.github.com/blog/2013/07/11/free-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I recently put a coupon up on <a href="https://twitter.com/poginate">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://alpha.app.net/poginate">App.net</a> offering ten people the opportunity to get a free copy of my book <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em>, which is still very much in <strong>alpha</strong>. But I figured attracting a few extra readers couldn’t do anything but help. </p>

<p>And in next to no time all ten free copies were gone, which is awesome. I’m not so much about the money on this one, I’m just enjoying writing it and really want to see it published and hopefully help a few people. </p>

<p>Anyway, it occurred to me that I hadn’t offered free copies to any of my faithful blog followers! So, here’s the deal: here’s another coupon code, also good for the first 10, nah, let’s say 20 people, but the condition is that I <em>really</em> would like any feedback you have about the book, even in this early state. Okay, ready? Here’s the skinny:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Go to <a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">https://leanpub.com/painless_vim</a></li>
  <li>buy the book using the coupon code <strong>Blog20</strong>. <sup id="fnref:paymor"><a href="#fn:paymor" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
  <li>Give me some awesome and useful feedback on the book either through the Leanpub site, as a comment on this site. Or ping me on <a href="https://twitter.com/poginate">Twitter</a>/<a href="https://alpha.app.net/poginate">App.net</a> with the hashtag #PainlessVim. However you get the feedback to me I will definitely take it into consideration and use it to improve the book.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:paymor">
      <p>And if you <em>want</em> to pay more than nothing I won’t stop you! Seriously! I’d be fine with it!<a href="#fnref:paymor" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
