<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: short | Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/categories/short/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-14T10:15:12-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://natedickson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Douglas Adams and JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/10/06/douglas-adams-and-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T15:20:18-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2014/10/06/douglas-adams-and-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was brushing up on some JavaScript for work and came across a problem that has bugged me before: testing for <code>NaN</code><sup id="fnref:notANumber"><a href="#fn:notANumber" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. I’ve never dug too deeply into this one, I’ve just known that if you try something like this:</p>

<p><code>javascript
	var a = NaN
	if (a == NaN){
	   //a is NaN, do something
	}
	else{
	   //a is a number, do something else
	}
</code></p>

<p>The code would always do something else. so I usually found a different way to solve the problem. </p>

<p>Today I actually dug into it and found that in JavaScript the value <code>NaN</code> has some odd properties:</p>

<ol>
  <li>It’s a number.</li>
  <li>It is the one value in JavaScript that can never equal itself. </li>
</ol>

<p>So that’s annoying, but actually lends itself to a very easy solution: if you want to test if a variable is <code>NaN</code> you can test it like this:</p>

<p><code>javascript
	if (a !== a){
		// a is NaN
	}else{
		// a is a number
	}
</code></p>

<p>But people who are good at JavaScript already know this. This is not news. </p>

<p>What struck me about this is that Douglas Adams invented a word for this kind of value: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>… a recipriversexcluson, a number whose existence can only be defined as being anything other than itself. 
Douglas Adams, *The Ultimate Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy (p. 345). Random House Publishing Group. Kindle Edition. *</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Somehow this made me actually like JavaScript more. </p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:notANumber">
      <p>If you don’t know, <code>NaN</code> is a special value meaning “Not a Number” and is used to check if the variable you’re working with actually has numerical data.<a href="#fnref:notANumber" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
