<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Writing | Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-07T13:31:01-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://natedickson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not During, But Due To NaNoWriMo]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/05/not-during-but-due-to-nanowrimo/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-05T10:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/05/not-during-but-due-to-nanowrimo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year marks my sixth year participating in <a href="http://nanowrimo.org/">NaNoWriMo</a>, and I’ve started wondering if there was really a <em>point</em> to writing a “novel” in a single month. Especially since I haven’t really developed any of them beyond the rough draft I wrote in November. </p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/nano_win.png" title="“National Novel Writing Month Winner” “National Novel Writing Month Winner”" > So, I “won” again this year, writing a book that I have absolutely no desire to pursue further. Which has made me wonder if I’m doing it wrong or if I need to maybe just give up on NaNoWriMo because it’s not helping me grow as a “real” writer. But then I realized something.</p>

<p>I never would have written <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em> if I hadn’t been taking part of NaNoWriMo every year. <em>Painless Vim</em> isn’t a novel, it’s not a wild flight of fancy that I pounded out in a month.<sup id="fnref:supposed"><a href="#fn:supposed" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  But there are a lot of things I learned from NaNoWriMo that made it possible for me to write <em>Painless Vim</em>. Some of the most important are: </p>

<ol>
  <li>Write every day. This is the first and only secret of writing, of course. </li>
  <li>Write your first draft like nobody is going to read it, because nobody <em>is</em> going to read it. You’ll revise it into something better. </li>
  <li>Write for yourself. There are others out there who are in the same place as you, and they’ll appreciate what you’ve written. </li>
  <li>Use Scrivener. <a href="http://www.favoritethingever.com/2010/10/scrivener/">I absolutely <em>love</em> Scrivener</a>, and six years of NaNo’ing has made it as comfortable as a well-worn pair of blue jeans for me. If I get up the energy I’ll write a post about how my Scrivener workflow looks one of these days. </li>
</ol>

<p>Now, I’m not saying that I’m the world’s best author. But I wrote a book and put it out there where people can buy it, which is something that never would have happened if it hadn’t been for National Novel Writing Month. And that’s enough to keep me coming back year after year.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:supposed">
      <p>It’s a tutorial book that was only <em>supposed</em> to take a month and has so far taken me about six.<a href="#fnref:supposed" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excerpt from Pacifica]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/01/excerpt-from-pacifica/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T07:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/12/01/excerpt-from-pacifica</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the best study of my main character, the one that I think most accurately captures who she thinks she is. </p>

<hr />

<p>The roadway sparkles and flows with light, a jeweled strand across the dark landscape. Cylee sat far up on a hill, the fresh, wild wind blowing her hair back. </p>

<p>She used to live in this place, this quiet, dark, outdoor world. Back before Pacifica, before the war…</p>

<p>The strings of lights eventually merge into the cities, connecting the nets of lights that represent civilization, mankind’s crowning jewels shining in the dark. And once you’re caught in that net it can feel like there’s nothing else, no other way to live. You can learn to depend on the Network, constant wireless streams of information flowing into and out of you at all times. You can learn to read the streets as you read the trees, feel the way the social wind is blowing just as you used to know how to read the fitful pre-dawn breezes. </p>

<p>And, in truth, Cylee was caught by that net. If she stayed out here for a few days or weeks her Spine would shut down and go from being an Augmentation to being thirty pounds of stiff dead metal. She’d be essentially blinded and deafened, her limbs left to their own strength. Even now she was half blind, her Spine out of range of the Network and therefore unable to give her the kind of information that made up the background noise of her daily life. Granted, she could still see every living, warm blooded thing that moved in the darkness, every rabbit, every bat, every bird was a blip on her augmented vision, their insane heart rates pounding like miniature thunder in her ears. </p>

<p>But she used to track them unaided. Used to be able to sense the movement of creatures that were string to remain hidden. She could feel the twitch in the grass that didn’t <em>quite</em> match the way the wind was moving. And she would raise her bow quietly, wait for the next movement…and…with a soft twang she would have breakfast.</p>

<p>Out of a sense of irony and frustration she considered raising her flechette thrower and pinning that rabbit to the ground, letting her Spine handle the fine details of getting her hand in the right position, but she stopped, realized she didn’t need the meat, and shouldn’t waste it. Pacifica had made her a perfect soldier, but it hadn’t entirely removed the true hunter she had been. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My NaNoWriMo Cover for This Year]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/10/31/my-nanowrimo-cover-for-this-year/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-31T11:34:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/10/31/my-nanowrimo-cover-for-this-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/assets/images/pacifica_cover.jpg" width="250" title="Pacifica Cover" >
This is a super-short post to show off what I’m going to be working on for <a href="http://nanowrimo.org">NaNoWriMo</a> this year. </p>

<p>I know that <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim/">Painless Vim</a></em> isn’t finished yet, although it’s very close, and basically all I’m doing is a little bit of cleanup and formatting. If you’ve been waiting with baited breath for <em>Painless Vim</em> to be finished fear not! I will still be working on the Little Vim Book that Could during the month of November. In fact, my goal is to have it completely finished. By December 1st, even while I’m “winning” NaNoWriMo for the sixth straight year. </p>

<p>In previous years I’ve been doing graduate level classes, having babies<sup id="fnref:babies"><a href="#fn:babies" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and changing jobs during NaNoWriMo, and I’ve always found time to make it work. What’s more, the impetus it gives me tends to help me get more done in the rest of my life as well. The saying about giving work to busy people still holds true. If I turn myself into a busy person I tend to be more capable overall. Until I freak out and melt down, of course. So I guess there’s still something to be said for balance. </p>

<h2 id="more-about-pacifica">More About Pacifica</h2>

<p>Which is all very nice, but you may possibly be interested in the book cover I’m showing off here. You’ve got questions, no doubt. Questions like “What’s it about?” “Who designed your cover?” “Would you be willing to let me redesign your cover, because it’s pretty bad?” </p>

<p>The answers are “I’ll tell you in a minute”, “I did in about two hours using Pixelmator”, and “Yes” in that order. I like playing with Pixelmator, but I’m not super great with it, and if there’s a graphic designer out there who wants to take a second pass at this I’d be happy to let you. </p>

<p>The book is my first foray into cyberpunk. It’s a near-future look at what’s its like to be on the losing side of a war for independence, and how to keep your pride even when you’ve got nothing left to be proud of. </p>

<p>If I remember (and have time) I’ll probably post excerpts through the month. Wether or not I actually develop <em>Pacifica</em> after November remains to be seen, but if I’ve learned anything from five successful NaNo’s its that even writing an ultimately wasted story isn’t wasted effort. I’ve learned something from every book I’ve written.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:babies">
      <p>Well, not me <em>personally</em>. <a href="#fnref:babies" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ulysses III: A Huge Leap Forward]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/04/04/ulysses-iii-a-huge-leap-forward/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-04T15:45:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/04/04/ulysses-iii-a-huge-leap-forward</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ll admit it, I’ve had a sick love/hate relationship with <a href="http://www.ulyssesapp.com/">Ulysses</a> for years. I first heard of it by way of <a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php">Scrivener</a>, my beloved freeform creative writing app. And the Ulysses of then just was not a thing of beauty. The interface had a lot of holdovers from early- or pre-OSX days, and was pretty cluttered (which is quite a statement, given <a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/gfx/ScrivShots/write_structure_revise.jpg">Scrivener’s interface</a>. I love Scrivener, but it’s clearly a <em>tool</em>…look, I’m off topic again.) and unfriendly. I could see some of the power that was inherent in the product, but it just wasn’t for me.</p>

<p>Well, A few days ago Ulysses III released a brand new version, and they <strong>nailed</strong> it. They took the bold step of abandoning everything they’d done before, threw out the interface entirely, and started over. They took a look at what the OSX world is doing now, in terms of interface, and did that. A very finder-like sidebar gives you access to all your text, organized based on where it lives. (iCloud, on your mac, or, if you have the <a href="http://daedalusapp.com/">Daedalus app</a> for iOS, in your Daedalus iCloud folder) Inside each folder you have your texts, (called “sheets”, as in “sheets of paper”) all of which are auto-saved at all times, so you don’t have to worry about hitting <code>⌘S</code> all the time. It’s a surprisingly slick and easy way to just sit down and <em>write</em> without worrying about filenames or sync options of any such things. You just start writing and worry about organization later, once you’ve got something out there. </p>

<h2 id="the-cons">The Cons</h2>
<p>It’s not all peaches and light, of course. The developers have pointed out that this is a 1.0 release, even if it <em>is</em> called Ulysses III. The app stores its files in <code>.ulysses</code> format, which isn’t interoperable with tools like Marked, which means its a little harder to get previews of your text post-Markdown-rendering. (It’s still quite possible, but not quite easy). It doesn’t natively handle <a href="http://fletcherpenney.net/multimarkdown/">MultiMarkdown</a>, but it exports multimarkdown-compatible footnotes. I’m guessing that the <code>.ulysses</code> file format is a bundle that wraps up all the images and keywords and notes and whatnot, but it does make interoperability with other apps a little harder. </p>

<p>But this is a minor gripe, and isn’t a flaw so much as a design decision that was clearly made with forethought. They decided that Ulysses was written as a creation app. You can share later, but create your text <em>first</em>. </p>

<p>All in all, I’m deeply impressed with the level of polish and attention that went into the latest version, and I’d recommend you pick it up.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
