<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: self-promotion | Nate Dickson]]></title>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/categories/self-promotion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://natedickson.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-14T10:15:12-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://natedickson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate Dickson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Books!]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/11/free-books/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-11T09:11:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/07/11/free-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I recently put a coupon up on <a href="https://twitter.com/poginate">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://alpha.app.net/poginate">App.net</a> offering ten people the opportunity to get a free copy of my book <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Painless Vim</a></em>, which is still very much in <strong>alpha</strong>. But I figured attracting a few extra readers couldn’t do anything but help. </p>

<p>And in next to no time all ten free copies were gone, which is awesome. I’m not so much about the money on this one, I’m just enjoying writing it and really want to see it published and hopefully help a few people. </p>

<p>Anyway, it occurred to me that I hadn’t offered free copies to any of my faithful blog followers! So, here’s the deal: here’s another coupon code, also good for the first 10, nah, let’s say 20 people, but the condition is that I <em>really</em> would like any feedback you have about the book, even in this early state. Okay, ready? Here’s the skinny:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Go to <a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">https://leanpub.com/painless_vim</a></li>
  <li>buy the book using the coupon code <strong>Blog20</strong>. <sup id="fnref:paymor"><a href="#fn:paymor" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
  <li>Give me some awesome and useful feedback on the book either through the Leanpub site, as a comment on this site. Or ping me on <a href="https://twitter.com/poginate">Twitter</a>/<a href="https://alpha.app.net/poginate">App.net</a> with the hashtag #PainlessVim. However you get the feedback to me I will definitely take it into consideration and use it to improve the book.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:paymor">
      <p>And if you <em>want</em> to pay more than nothing I won’t stop you! Seriously! I’d be fine with it!<a href="#fnref:paymor" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Painless Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/22/introducing-painless-vim/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-22T12:47:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/05/22/introducing-painless-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/painless_cover.png" title="Painless Vim Cover" >
I’m excited to announce the availability of <em>Painless Vim</em>, my new (indeed, still in progress) book on the ever powerful vim editor! While the book is still in progress, you can pick up a copy at <a href="https://leanpub.com/painless_vim">Leanpub</a> right now and make suggestions to help guide the development of this book. I’m very impressed by the Leanpub system, allowing authors to write their books out in the open and get feedback along the way. </p>

<h2 id="why-another-vim-tutorial">Why Another Vim Tutorial?</h2>

<p>I started thinking about writing this book when I realized I <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/2010/07/29/everyone-who-tried-to-convince-me-to-use-vim-was-wrong/">wasn’t the only developer</a> who has tried to use vim and was put off by the vast majority of vim training available. Vim is really very developer friendly, but a lot of the teaching resources for vim are anything but. My goal is to take the best of what I have picked up in my journey to vim and present it in a way that helps other people get over the initial hurdle and into the good parts of the editor.</p>

<p>I’ll be writing quite a bit about the development process of the book and the workflow involved. Watch this space!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing A.K.A.: The Alias Manager]]></title>
    <link href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/04/12/introducing-a-dot-k-a-dot-the-alias-manager/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-12T11:33:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/04/12/introducing-a-dot-k-a-dot-the-alias-manager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the joys of moving from a Windows machine at work to OSX is that I’m back to having access to the unix command line. The downside, of course, long commands that I <a href="http://xkcd.com/1168/">usually get wrong</a>. </p>

<p>Which is why I spent some time a few weeks ago creating <a href="http://natedickson.com/A.K.A./">A.K.A.</a> Simply put, A.K.A. is a simple way to manage all the aliases that you usually put into your shell of choice’s startup file without editing your dot files by hand or cluttering up your profile when you could be cluttering up a completely separate file. </p>

<p>Now all you have to do is add <code>source ~/.alias</code> and use this script to keep everything nice and organized.</p>

<p>Again, it’s a simple difference; If you know what aliases are you probably aren’t afraid of editing dot files, but <code>aka</code> removes the friction of pulling up your favorite editor, finding where all your aliases are, saving, etc. Everything is a single command issued right at the prompt, all the saving and moving around is handled for you. The result is that I have far <strong>more</strong> aliases, and far more <strong>useful</strong> aliases, because I can add them or change them without breaking my flow. If I realize that I hate typing <code>git status</code> I just run <code>aka -a gs "git status"</code> and now I’ve got a much shorter version of that command. The downside, of course, is that I get intensely frustrated using anyone else’s computer where <code>gs</code> doesn’t work. But I can cope with that.</p>

<p>My favorite (slightly under-documented) command is <code>aka -L</code>, which outputs a nicely formatted list of all your aliases and what they do when you run them. It’s a simple thing, but I like it.</p>

<p>In the event that you actually decide to use this feel free to put suggestions or feature requests or comments either on this page’s comment line or on the <a href="https://github.com/PogiNate/A.K.A.">github page</a>. </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
